Mss.B.Os73
American Philosophical Society
W. J. V. (Winthrop John Van Leuven) Osterhout papers, 1894-1961
Mss.B.Os73
American Philosophical Society
3.0 Linear feet Ca. 2500 items
Ca. 2500 items, 3 linear feet.
This collection contains correspondence, drafts of papers, the manuscript of an unpublished book, and photographs. Osterhout's interest in the electrophysiology of plants is documented, as well as his professional career at the University of California, Berkeley; Harvard University; and the Rockefeller Institute.
Osterhout, W. J. V., (Winthrop John Van Leuven), 1871-1964
Box 1-6
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Marion Irwin Osterhout and accessioned, 12/--/1962 (1962 2280ms). Additional papers donated by Marion Irwin Osterhout and accessioned, 11/20/1968 (1868 2717ms).
Biographical/Historical note
Osterhout was a physiologist and worked primarily on the electric conductivity of plant cells. He was the editor of the Journal of General Physiology from 1919 to 1964.
Physiology, Biochemistry, and Biophysics Note
The Osterhout Collection records the scientific career of Winthrop John Van Leuven Osterhout from the 1890s to the 1950s. The correspondence, drafts of papers, lectures, and photographs document significant trends in American life sciences. Having begun at the botany department at Brown University, Osterhout continued working in botany at Berkeley (where he completed his doctorate in 1899) on problems of cell division in plants. While a professor of botany at Harvard (1909-1924) he began his innovative research program on the physico-chemical properties of membranes and cytoplasm of algae cells. He expanded this program (related to neurophysiology) after succeeding his late mentor Jacques Loeb in 1924 as head of the physiology department at the Rockefeller Institute. During these years Osterhout was also associated with the marine laboratories in Pacific Grove, Woods Hole, and Bermuda, and with the Agassiz Museum; he was also a founding editor of the Journal of General Physiology.
As his papers show, Osterhout's scientific path bridged two major intellectual traditions: the agricultural and the medical, linking studies in botany and zoology with the new discipline of general physiology. His research program also reflected the shift in emphasis from morphological to physico-chemical problems in physiology. Indeed, his studies at the Rockefeller Institute of membrane permeability and bio-electric phenomena merged important areas in biochemistry, biophysics, and physiology (especially neurophysiology), as is reflected in his correspondence with other leaders in these fields.
Abderhalden, Emil, 1877-1950 Correspondence (6 items) 1912-1936, n.d. German
Abel, John Jacob, 1857-1938 Correspondence (1 item) 1925 English
American Association for the Advancement of Science ( On the organization of sessions in plant physiology.) Correspondence (37 items) 1913-1925, 1958 English
American Society of Plant Physiologists ( Includes material on European research.) Correspondence (3 items) 1925 English
Arrhenius, Svante, 1859-1927 ( On topics in physical chemistry and biophysics, cultural issues, institutional involvements, Nobel Prizes, politics, the war and the international scientific community. Arrhenius refers to his visit at Berkeley and his friendship with Jacques Loeb, and later (1911) to his visit at the Rockefeller Institute. He conveys his impressions of science in the United States and other countries, his reflections on books and scientific issues, and gives descriptions of the research in his laboratory (1913). The correspondence during the war is filled with details about German science and the impact of the war on Europe's scientific community. Postwar letters describe vividly the plight of the average person, as well as the changing attitude toward German science. Of particular interest are the letters concerning the congress of physiology in Paris (from which Germans were excluded) and the politics of the Nobel Prize (circa 1920s). These letters are a rich source on European science and on the relationships between European and American science. They also reveal a great deal about Arrhenius as a scientist, thinker, and organizer of international science.) Correspondence (30 items) 1906-1924 English
Bergmann, M. (Max), 1886-1944 Correspondence (1 item) 1942 English
Bioelectric Potentials ( Conference papers.) Records (56 pages) 1946 English
Brierley, William B. ( Organization of the Rothamsted Experimental Station, and correspondence on postwar conditions in England.) Correspondence (1 item (5 pages)) 1925 English
Bronk, Detlev W. (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975 ( Includes Introduction to Osterhout Memorial Lecture, 1971.) Correspondence (35 items) 1945-1971 English
Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926 ( Plant breeding.) Correspondence (13 items) 1897-1909 English
Cannon, Walter B. (Walter Bradford), 1871-1945 ( Scientific correspondence.) Correspondence (5 items) 1925-1944 English
Cole, Kenneth Stewart, 1900-1984 ( On biophysics.) Correspondence (15 items) 1944-1967 English
Conant, James Bryant, 1893-1978 ( Scientific correspondence. Includes essay, "On the Basicity of Cresyl Blue.") Correspondence (3 items) 1930, 1944 English
Crozier, William John, 1892-1955 ( On the organization of research in the life sciences.) Correspondence (10 items) 1933, 1955 English
Donnan, F. G. (Frederick George), 1870-1956 ( On plant physiology.) Correspondence (6 items) 1929-1940 English
Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946 ( On major trends in cytology, physiology, neurophysiology, and biophysics, and progress reports.) Correspondence (Approximately 200 items) 1924-1940 English
Kirkwood, John Gamble, 1907-1959 ( Scientific exchanges.) Correspondence (6 items) 1942-1955 English
Lillie, Frank Rattray, 1870-1947 ( Informative letters on Lillie's activities at Woods Hole and other institutions of the life sciences.) Correspondence (2 items) 1922-1936 English
Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924 ( Scientific, administrative, and personal aspects of Loeb's tenure at Berkeley. There are also interesting anecdotes of Loeb, which illuminate the man and his work.) Correspondence (2 folders) 1909-1922 English
Merriam, John C. (John Campbell), 1869-1945 ( On research at the Tortuga Station.) Correspondence (2 items) 1926-1927 English
Morgan, Thomas Hunt, 1866-1945 ( Administrative correspondence.) Correspondence (5 items) 1924-1933 English
Northrop, John Howard, 1891-1987 ( Scientific correspondence and editorial communications relating to the Journal of General Physiology.) Correspondence (21 items) 1934-1964 English
O'Neill, Edmond, 1859-1933 ( An important letter about Loeb and developing the life sciences at Berkeley.) Correspondence (1 item) 1910 English
Osterhout, W. J. V. (Winthrop John Van Leuven), 1871-1964 ( Manuscript materials including records on the Bermuda Station, administrative issues in general physiology, and Osterhout's Ph.D. thesis on pre-Mendelian chromosome research.) Manuscripts (Approximately 10 folders) 1899-1961 English
Parker, George Howard, 1864-1955 ( General physiology at Harvard, and science and politics.) Correspondence (41 items) 1913-1953 English
Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972 ( General physiology and politics at Harvard.) Correspondence (5 items) 1928-1954 English
Stanley, Wendell M. (Wendell Meredith), 1904-1971 ( Include references to Stanley's work at Osterhout's laboratory.) Correspondence (4 items) 1937-1953 English
Vries, Hugo de, 1848-1935 ( Impressions of American research institutions of life sciences.) Correspondence (16 items) 1902-1935 English
Additional Biographical Notes:
Svante Arrhenius received the Nobel Prize in 1903 for his studies of electrolytic dissociation in solutions, work which was on the borderland of physics and chemistry. Two years later he assumed the directorship of the Nobel Institute for Physical Chemistry, a post he held until his death. His proclivity for interdisciplinary topics led him to apply principles from physical chemistry to immunology and to advance theories of cosmology and the origin of life ( Worlds in the Making, 1908). His broad scientific interests and his position in the Nobel Institute placed him at the center of international communities of physical and life scientists.
W. J. V. Osterhout met Arrhenius at Berkeley, where Arrhenius was a visiting professor shortly after being awarded the Nobel Prize. The friendship which developed between the two men is reflected in their correspondence.
Arrhenius, Svante, 1859-1927; Blinks, L. R.; Brierley, William B.; Bronk, Detlev W., (Detlev Wulf), 1897-1975; Burbank, Luther, 1849-1926; Crozier, William John, 1892-1955; Fenn, Wallace O.; Flexner, Simon, 1863-1946; Gasser, Herbert Spencer, 1888-1963; Harvard University.; Loeb, Jacques, 1859-1924; Northrop, John Howard, 1891-1987; Parker, George Howard, 1864-1955; Rockefeller Institute.; Rothamsted Experimental Station.; Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972; Shedlovsky, Theodore, 1898-1976; Strasburger, Eduard, 1844-1912; University of California, Berkeley.; Vries, Hugo de,1848-1935.; Wheeler, Benjamin I. (Benjamin Ide), 1854-1927; Agricultural experiment stations -- England.; Electrophysiology of plants.; Manuscripts (for publication).; Photoprints.; Plant cells and tissues -- Electric properties.; Plant physiology.; Science publishing.
- Photographs, A collection of photographs from the W.J.V. (Winthrop John Van Leuven) Osterhout papers, including representative images from his work in Bermuda and Harvard as well as a number of personal and family photographs. Images are arranged roughly in the following order: Osterhout portraits in chronological order; portraits of family, friends and coworkers; images of laborartories and equipment; misc.
  - W.J.V. Osterhout, age 2., 1873; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length formal portrait of Osterhout leaning against a support.
  - Osterhout, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait of Osterhout.
  - Osterhout, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 view portrait, formal.
  - Osterhout, formal portrait with bow tie and mustache., 1.0 Photograph(s); Half length formal portrait.
    General note
    Inscription on back identifies this image as Osterhout in California.
  - W. J. V. Osterhout, half length, formal., ca. 1915; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 view portrait of Osterhout in brown suit.
  - W.J.V. Osterhout, bust, sitting, formal portrait., ca. 1930; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait of Osterhout in glasses.
  - Mother of W.J.V. Osterhout, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Bust lenght formal portrait of W. J. V. Osterhout's mother.
  - Father of W.J.V Osterhout, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Bust length formal portrait of W. J. V. Osterhout's father.
  - D. H. Lehmer [?]., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait, bust length.
    Signature on back is hard to read, subject uncertain.
  - Dr. and Mrs. Svante Arrhenius, formal portrait., 1.0 Photograph(s)
  - E. A. Strasburger, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait of Strasburger, with mustache.
    Hand written note on back of photograph: "George Howard Parker, Professor of zoology at Harvard. He was A.B., M. A., Ph.D. from Harvard and never had a job elsewhere. He was very popular and highly admired. Note how simple his laboratory was, yet he became famous."
  - G. H. Parker, formal portrait., 1929; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 length formal portrait.
  - G. H. Parker, in laboratory., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Parker, sitting at desk in laboratory.
  - G. H. Parker, seated, holding hat., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length portrait of Parker seated outside, holding hat.
  - George Escol Sellers, 1896., 1.0 Photograph(s); Exterior view of house and porch with Sellers sitting on steps, cat and dog nearby.
  - Hugo de Vries., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal bust length portrait of Hugo de Vries.
  - Pofessor Asa Gray, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); 3/4 view, bust length formal portrait, carte de visite.
  - R. Huber, formal portrait, holding eye glasses., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Bust length portrait of Huber.
    Hand written note on back of photograph: "Huber and his wife were good friends of Marion [?] and W. J. V. Osterhout. W. J. V. O. helped Huber leave Germany and settle permanently in U.S.A. Merkel Jacobs agreed to receive Huber. The last words Huber said to the Osterhouts as he was driving away from Woods Hole, 'You are both wonderful people. I love you both.' He died subsequently. Mrs. Huber was already dead. They maintained their dignity in spite of the humiliating circumstances suffered by them in Germany."
  - S. E. Hill, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal portrait of S. E. Hill, wearing glasses.
  - Sir Joseph D. Hooker, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); Carte de visite, formal portrait with glasses.
  - Roland Thaxter, holding dog, 1928., 1928, August 28; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 lenght view of Rolan Thaxter standing outside, holdin dog.
    Inscription under photograph: "Roland Thaxter (Kittery Point, Main, Aug. 28, 1928.) [?] sends his regards and very many thanks for your congratulations."
  - Formal portrait of Olof Arrhenius and S. Arrhenius., 1911; 1.0 Item(s); Half length view of Olof holding a small child, greeting card.
  - William A. Setchell, formal portrait., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); 3/4 view formal portrait.
    Hand written note on back: "To W. J. V. Osterhout -- his dearest friend, with sincerest regards, William A. Setchell."
  - Lawrence Blinks, Bermuda, 1927, 1.0 Photograph(s); Blinks holding telephone receiver to ear.
  - [W. J. V. Osterhout] full length, informal, standing outside with gigantic algae., 1895; 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout on wooden walkway beside building looking at gigantic algae.
    Instription at bottom of photograph: "nereocystis gigantia - San Pedro, Calif. - Dec. 1895."
  - Leo Loeb, seated at table, looking into microscope., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Candid profile portrait of Leo Loeb.
  - Osterhout and Lawrence Blinks in row boat., 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout sitting in, and Blinks standing beside, row boat.
  - Osterhout in Bermuda laboratory, 1922., 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout standing beside table with beakers.
  - Osterhout in snowshoes., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout outside in snow, with foot on bench, with snowshoe displayed.
  - Winter scene with people standing in snow with skies., 1.0 Photograph(s); Seven people in snow with skies, trees in background.
    Hand written note on back of photograph: "Every Sunday Osterhout and Parker took many graduate students and professors out walking and sking, at Harvard."
  - Osterhout with Otto Loleoi [?], Woods Hole, 1951, 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of two men standing outside, tree in background, Osterhout wearing hat.
  - Osterhout in laboratory, Rockefeller Institute, 1952., 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout seated in laboratory with lab coat.
  - Jacques Loeb, Robert Less [?] and Leonard Rigns [?], Woods Hole., 1.0 Photograph(s); Three men on porch, two sitting in rocking chairs, one standing.
  - Louis Brandeis and Jacques Loeb., 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Brandeis and Loeb standing outside, building in background.
  - Winthrop John Van Osterhout, full length, profile, informal, seated at the M.B.L., Woods Hole, Mass., 1950; 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout working at desk, shadows in foreground, window in background.
  - Ralph Lillie, Walter [Garvey], W. J. V. Osterhout, E. G. Couklin, Merkel Jacobs, A. P. [Mathlos], Robert F. Loeb, E. N. Harvey, and G. H. Clowes formal, standing and seated at the Marine Biological Laboratory, Woods Hole., 1950; 1.0 Photograph(s); Formal group protrait of nine men sitting and standing.
  - W. J. V. Osterhout, [?] Traju, [?] Luche, [?] Shedlovsky, and [?] Parpart, 3/4 length, informal, standing at the Marine Biological Laboratory, at Woods Hole, Massachusetts., 1951, August 2; 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout holding portfolio and making a fist with right hand, four men in background.
  - W. J. V. Osterhout, Jacques, Loeb, Hugo de Vries, and others full length, informal, standing outside at the University of California., 1905; 1.0 Photograph(s); Eleven men and one women standing out doors in hats.
  - W. J. V. Osterhout and others, half length, profile, informal, standing., 1951, August 2; 1.0 Photograph(s); Candid profile of Osterhout surrounded by standing men smiling and laughing.
  - W. J. V. Osterhout and wife, half length, profile, informal, he is standing, she is seated in laboratory at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research., 1951; 1.0 Photograph(s); Osterhout and wife in laboratory.
  - Exterior view of Bermuda laboratory., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Exterior view of building with trees in background.
  - Exterior view of laboratory and grounds in Bermuda., 1.0 Photograph(s); Exterior view of building, with trees in forefront.
  - California laboratory of W.J.V Osterhout., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Internal view of laboratory with plants on tables and people near windows.
  - Laboratory equipment of W.J.V. Osterhout., n. d.; 1.0 Photograph(s); Internal view of laboratory and equipment.
    Hand written note on back of photograph: "Apparatus devised by W. J. V. Osterhout for determining electrical [?] response in single cells of Nitella (plants)."
  - Liberty Bell postcard., n. d.; 1.0 Item(s); Color image of Liberty Bell.